# ANTON JERAN RATNARAJAH

8500 48th Avenue, College Park, MD 20740 | jeran@umd.edu | (301) 742-5701 | website

## PERSONAL STATEMENT

I am a 5th year PhD student at the University of Maryland, College Park advised by Professor Dinesh Manocha. My research area is broadly in building multi-modal machine learning models to create high-quality sound experiences in interactive applications.

## **EDUCATION**

## University of Maryland - College Park

College Park, MD, USA

PhD in Electrical and Computer Engineering

Aug. 2019 - Present (2024 expected)

Cumulative GPA: 3.88/4.0

## University of Moratuwa

Moratuwa, Sri Lanka

Bachelor of Science in Engineering

Feb. 2014 - Jan. 2018

Cumulative GPA: 3.91/4.2

## SELECTED Publications (Multimodal)

## $AV ext{-}RIR: Audio-Visual Room Impulse Response Estimation$

Anton Ratnarajah, Sreyan Ghosh, Sonal Kumar, Purva Chiniya, Dinesh Manocha

**CVPR 2024** 

# Listen2Scene: Interactive material-aware binaural sound propagation for reconstructed

3D scenes

Anton Ratnarajah, Dinesh Manocha

IEEE VR 2024

## AdVerb: Visually Guided Audio Dereverberation

Sanjoy Chowdhury, Sreyan Ghosh, Subhrajyoti Dasgupta, **Anton Ratnarajah**, Utkarsh Tyagi, Dinesh Manocha. ICCV 2023

## MESH2IR: Neural Acoustic Impulse Response Generator for Complex 3D Scenes

Anton Ratnarajah, Zhenyu Tang, Rohith Aralikatti, Dinesh Manocha

ACM Multimedia 2022 (Oral)

#### GWA: A Large Geometric-Wave Acoustic Dataset for Audio Deep Learning

Zhenyu Tang, Rohith Aralikatti, **Anton Ratnarajah**, Dinesh Manocha

SIGGRAPH 2022

## SELECTED PUBLICATIONS (AUDIO AND SPEECH PROCESSING)

#### Towards Improved Room Impulse Response Estimation for Speech Recognition

**Anton Ratnarajah**, Ishwarya Ananthabhotla, Vamsi Krishna Ithapu, Pablo Hoffmann, Dinesh Manocha, Paul Calamia ICASSP 2023

## FAST-RIR: Fast neural diffuse room impulse response generator

**Anton Ratnarajah**, Shi-Xiong Zhang, Meng Yu, Zhenyu Tang, Dinesh Manocha, Dong Yu

ICASSP 2022

## IR-GAN: Room Impulse Response Generator for Far-field Speech Recognition

Anton Ratnarajah, Zhenyu Tang, Dinesh Manocha

INTERSPEECH 2021

#### TS-RIR: Translated synthetic room impulse responses for speech augmentation

Anton Ratnarajah, Zhenyu Tang, Dinesh Manocha

IEEE ASRU 2021

#### Improving Reverberant Speech Separation with multi-stage training and curriculum learning

Rohith Aralikatti, Anton Ratnarajah, Zhenyu Tang, Dinesh Manocha

IEEE ASRU 2021

## M3-AUDIODEC: Multi-channel multi-speaker multi-spatial audio codec

Anton Ratnarajah, Shi-Xiong Zhang, Dong Yu

Arxiv

#### Work Experience

Research Intern May. 2023 – Aug. 2023

Tencent America Bellevue, Washington, United States

Implemented an innovative neural spatial audio codec for efficient compression of multi-channel (binaural) speech in both single and multi-speaker scenarios while retaining the spatial location information of each speaker.

#### Research Scientist Intern

May. 2022 – Nov. 2022

META

Redmond, Washington, United States

Implemented a novel algorithm to estimate room impulse response from a reverberant speech.

Research Intern May. 2021 – Aug. 2021

Tencent America

Bellevue, Washington, United States

Implemented a neural-network-based fast diffuse room impulse response generator (FAST-RIR) for generating room impulse responses (RIRs) for a given acoustic environment.

**Engineer** Feb. 2018 – Jul. 2019

Wave Computing

Colombo, Sri Lanka

Developed machine learning applications for Wave Computing's Dataflow Processing Unit (DPU) Architecture using Wave Flow Graph (WFG), a data flow description language developed by Wave Computing. Compiled and simulated the designs in Wave Computing's complete EDA toolchain. Debugged and proposed suggestions to improve the toolchain and the architecture.

Research Intern Aug. 2016 – Dec. 2016

HESL Lab, Nanyang Technological University

Singapore

Successfully completed a project titled "Low complexity techniques for Vehicle Localization and Tracking" under the guidance of Dr. Lam Siew Kei.

## TEACHING EXPERIENCE

#### ENEE 245: Digital Circuits and Systems Laboratory

University of Maryland

Teaching Assistant for Associate Professor Manoj Franklin

 $Spring \ 2022$ 

CMSC 742: Algorithms in Machine Learning: Guarantees and Analyses

University of Maryland

Teaching Assistant for Professor Furong Huang

Fall 2021

ENEE 630: Advanced Digital Signal Processing

University of Maryland

Teaching Assistant for Professor K. J. Ray Liu

Fall 2020

**ENEE 425: Digital Signal Processing** 

University of Maryland

Teaching Assistant for Associate Professor Behtash Babadi

Spring 2020

**ENEE 425: Digital Signal Processing** 

University of Maryland

Teaching Assistant for Professor Carol Espy-Wilson

Fall 2019

## Academic Services

• I served as a reviewer for the ACM Multimedia 2023, ACM UIST 2023, IEEE VR 2023, MERCON 2019.

## Honors and Awards

- Won B.Sc. grant for outstanding SMCS B.Sc. thesis work from the IEEE SMCS Thesis Grant Initiative in 2018.
- Became Runner-Up in the Startathon Competition organized by Nanyang Technological University, Singapore in 2016.
- Our project titled Forensic Video Analytics Software was awarded Gold Medal in the "Tertiary Student Project (Technology)" Category on the 20th National Best Quality ICT Awards, in Sri Lanka.

## Coursework

**Artificial Intelligence**: Deep Learning for Audio-to-Audio Processing, Foundations of Deep Learning, Algorithms in Machine Learning: Guarantees and Analyses

Signal Processing: Speech and Audio Processing, Random Processes in Communication and Control, Advanced Digital

Signal Processing, Information Theory Other: Compilers and Optimization

## TECHNICAL SKILLS

Languages: Python, C/C++, Java, Matlab Public Libraries: Pytorch, Tensorflow, OpenCV

Software and Tools: Kaldi, Latex